American Association of University Professors
© 2005 University of Connecticut
American Association of University Professors, University of Connecticut Chapter Records.
undated, 1931-1981.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
American Association of University Professors, University of Connecticut Chapter.
3 linear feet.
MSS19980132
The UConn Chapter was established on 27 April 1932 when the constitution was adopted and officers elected. The Chapter title changed several times, reflecting the growth and development of the institution: Connecticut Agricultural College (1932-1933), Connecticut State College (1933-1939), and University of Connecticut (1939-present). The purpose of the national organization is to promote a “powerful body of informed opinion among university teachers and investigators of America” through the combined works of the local chapters. The national association establishes standards on such subjects as “academic freedom, tenure, and ethics” which, it hopes, will be actively supported by the local chapters.
History
The UConn Chapter was established on 27 April 1932 when the constitution was adopted and officers elected. The Chapter title changed several times, reflecting the growth and development of the institution: Connecticut Agricultural College (1932-1933), Connecticut State College (1933-1939), and University of Connecticut (1939-present). The purpose of the national organization is to promote a “powerful body of informed opinion among university teachers and investigators of America” through the combined works of the local chapters. The national association establishes standards on such subjects as “academic freedom, tenure, and ethics” which, it hopes, will be actively supported by the local chapters.
Information quoted from American Association of University Professors, “Chapter Organization and Management,” in the bound volume Minute Book: 1932-1957, 1st item, p. 1, Series I.
Arrangement
Series I: Minutes, Newsletters and Calls to meeting ( 1933-1970 ) includes calls to meetings, agendas, newsletters, and minutes with occasional correspondence and reports interfiled. There are no minutes for the years 1951-1952. Arranged chronologically.
Series II: Reports and Resolutions ( 1936-1962 ) is composed of various reports developed by the UConn chapter of the AAUP and the National AAUP filed in chronological order. The reports cover a wide range of topics.
Series III: Correspondence ( 1931-1965 ) contains correspondence to and from the national headquarters of the AAUP; correspondence to and from other chapters, calls to meetings and some reports. There are no records for the years 1946-1949. Files are arranged chronologically by year. Correspondence for 1959-1961 is further broken down by subject.
Series IV: Chapter letters ( 1933-1967 ) consists of mailings from national headquarters, Washington, D.C. on topics of general concern. There are no chapter letters for 1946-1949. Arranged chronologically.
Series V: Membership ( undated, 1932-1966 ) includes local membership lists and national lists of those nominated for membership. There are no records from the years 1952-1953, 1957-1958, 1963-1964 and 1964-1965. Arranged chronologically.
Series VI: General File ( undated, 1936-1947 ) contains such items as sample questionnaires for chapter activities, and newspaper clippings.
Series VII: AAUP contracts ( 1979-1981 ) holds two copies of the collective bargaining agreement between the University of Connecticut Board of Trustees and the University of Connecticut Chapter of the American Association of University Professors, 1 July 1979 - 30 June 1981.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Minutes.; Reports.
Occupations:
Professional education association.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The UConn Chapter of the AAUP donated the collection to Archives & Special Collections prior to 1998.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Minutes, Newsletters and Calls to meetings, 1932-1970
  - Minute book (bound volume), 1932-1957 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Secretary records, 1952-1954; (2 bound volumes) (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Calls to meetings, 1951-1953 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Minutes and calls to meetings, 1953-1954 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Minutes and calls to meetings, 1954-1955 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Minutes and calls to meetings, 1955-1956 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1956-1957 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1957-1958 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1958-1959 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1959-1960 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 1960-1961 (Box 2:, Folder 11)
  - Minutes, newsletters, calls to meetings, 1961-1962 (Box 2:, Folder 12)
  - Newsletters calls to meetings, 1962-1963 (Box 2:, Folder 13)
  - Minutes, newsletters, calls to meetings, 1963-1964 (Box 2:, Folder 14)
  - Minutes, newsletters, calls to meetings, 1964-1965 (Box 2:, Folder 15)
  - Minutes, newsletters, calls to meetings, 1965-1966 (Box 2:, Folder 16)
  - Minutes, newsletters, calls to meetings, 1966-1967 (Box 2:, Folder 17)
  - Minutes, calls to meetings, 1967-1968 (Box 2:, Folder 18)
  - Minutes, newsletters, calls to meetings, 1968-1969 (Box 2:, Folder 19)
  - Minutes, newsletters, calls to meetings, 1969-1970 (Box 2:, Folder 20)
- Series II: Reports and Resolutions, 1936-1962
  - Sabbatical Leave and Leave of Absence, 1936 (Box 3:, Folder 21)
  - Statement of Principles, 1940 (Box 3:, Folder 22)
  - Teaching Load, 1944 (Box 3:, Folder 23)
  - Reports, Economic Status, Salaries, 1945-1960 (Box 3:, Folder 24)
  - Senate Reorganization, 1947? (Box 3:, Folder 25)
  - Study of College Training, 1951 (Box 3:, Folder 26)
  - Freshman-Sophomore Counseling Report, 1951 (Box 3:, Folder 27)
  - Purchasing Committee Report (Prelim.), 1952 (Box 3:, Folder 28)
  - Proposal for Academic Freedom, 1951-1953 (Box 3:, Folder 29)
  - Social Security, 1952 (Box 3:, Folder 30)
  - Academic Freedom, 1952-1953 (Box 3:, Folder 31)
  - Library Report (Circ. To non-members), 1953 (Box 3:, Folder 32)
  - Central Stores Report, 1953 (Box 3:, Folder 33)
  - Chicago Meetings, 1953 (Box 3:, Folder 34)
  - Library Committee Reports, 1953, 1955-1959 (Box 3:, Folder 35)
  - Senate Elections Committee, 1954 (Box 3:, Folder 36)
  - Milieu Report, 1955? (Box 3:, Folder 37)
  - Library Committee, 1955 (Box 3:, Folder 38)
  - Faculty-Administration Report, 1959 (Box 3:, Folder 39)
  - Academic Quality, 1959-1960 (Box 3:, Folder 40)
  - TAF Committee, 1959-1960 (Box 3:, Folder 41)
  - Trustee-Faculty Consultation Resolution, 1959-1960 (Box 3:, Folder 42)
  - University Capital Outlay Project, 1959-1960 (Box 3:, Folder 43)
  - Faculty Salaries, 1960 (Box 3:, Folder 44)
  - Exit Interview Report, 1960 (Box 3:, Folder 45)
  - Quality of Education, Utilization of Resources and Personnel Problems, 1960 (Box 3:, Folder 46)
  - Legislative Liaison, 1960-1961 (Box 3:, Folder 47)
  - Faculty Participation in College and University Government, 1962 (Box 3:, Folder 48)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1949-1952 (Box 3:, Folder 49)
- Series III: Correspondence, 1931-1965
  - General, 1931-1945 (Box 4:, Folder 50)
  - General, 1931-1945 (Box 4:, Folder 51)
  - General, 1948-1949 (Box 4:, Folder 52)
  - General, 1949-1950 (Box 4:, Folder 53)
  - General, 1950-1951 (Box 4:, Folder 54)
  - General, 1951-1952 (Box 4:, Folder 55)
  - General, 1952-1953 (Box 4:, Folder 56)
  - General, 1953-1954 (Box 4:, Folder 57)
  - General, 1954-1955 (Box 4:, Folder 58)
  - General, 1955-1956 (Box 4:, Folder 59)
  - General, 1956-1957 (Box 4:, Folder 60)
  - General, 1957-1958 (Box 4:, Folder 61)
  - General, 1958-1959 (Box 4:, Folder 62)
  - Administrative and Local, 1959-1960 (Box 4:, Folder 63)
  - National, 1959-1960 (Box 4:, Folder 64)
  - Other Chapters, 1959-1960 (Box 4:, Folder 65)
  - Washington (headquarters), 1960-1961 (Box 4:, Folder 66)
  - Liaison with AFT, 1960-1961 (Box 4:, Folder 67)
  - State Government and Legislature, 1960-1961 (Box 4:, Folder 68)
  - Administration, 1960-1961 (Box 4:, Folder 69)
  - National, 1961-1962 (Box 4:, Folder 70)
  - General, 1963-1964 (Box 4:, Folder 71)
  - General, 1964-1965 (Box 4:, Folder 72)
- Series IV: Chapter Letters, 1933-1967
  - Chapter letters, 1933-1945 (Box 5:, Folder 73)
  - From National office, 1950-1958 (Box 5:, Folder 74)
  - Washington office, 1959-1967 (Box 5:, Folder 75)
- Series V: Membership, undated, 1932-1966
  - Officers, UConn Chapter, undated (Box 6:, Folder 76)
  - Membership, 1932-1950 (Box 6:, Folder 77)
  - Regulations, undated (Box 6:, Folder 78)
  - Lists, 1951 (Box 6:, Folder 79)
  - Membership, 1953-1954 (Box 6:, Folder 80)
  - Membership, 1954-1955 (Box 6:, Folder 81)
  - Membership, 1955-1956 (Box 6:, Folder 82)
  - Membership, 1956-1957 (Box 6:, Folder 83)
  - Membership, 1958-1959 (Box 6:, Folder 84)
  - Membership, 1959-1960 (Box 6:, Folder 85)
  - Membership, 1960-1961 (Box 6:, Folder 86)
  - Membership, 1961-1962 (Box 6:, Folder 87)
  - Membership, 1962-1963 (Box 6:, Folder 88)
  - Membership, 1965-1966 (Box 6:, Folder 89)
  - List, undated (Box 6:, Folder 90)
- Series VI: General File, undated, 1936-1947
  - Research project questionnaire, undated (Box 6:, Folder 91)
  - Chapter Activities questionnaire, 1936 (Box 6:, Folder 92)
  - Chapter Activities questionnaire, 1949 (Box 6:, Folder 93)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 6:, Folder 94)
  - Regional Conferences, undated (Box 6:, Folder 95)
  - Storrs and Fort Trumbull AAUP, 1947 (Box 6:, Folder 96)
- Series VII: AAUP Contracts, 1979-1981